<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Joe Carrano</title><link>https://carrano.org/</link><description>Recent content on Joe Carrano</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>CC-BY</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 04:00:50 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://carrano.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Hello World</title><link>https://carrano.org/2021/05/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 04:00:50 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://carrano.org/2021/05/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi there! I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to break ground on a new website for myself that&amp;rsquo;s more under my control and at my own domain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m moving away from my old site &lt;a href="https://josephcarrano.wordpress.com">josephcarrano.wordpress.com&lt;/a> and casting it into the abandoned graveyard. In recent years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been loath to create new posts not only because I&amp;rsquo;m lazy but also because I hate the thought of publishing content to URLs that could easily break.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite this worry, I won&amp;rsquo;t be migrating content at the moment or setting up redirects because I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like paying WordPress for the redirect service and it&amp;rsquo;s simple enough to leave it there neglected as it has been for the last few years. I&amp;rsquo;m mainly leaving it up in the interest of preventing link rot on the few posts that people found useful. If you want to check out the posts there, they should remain as long as wordpress.com remains free and functioning online. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll reconsider this later.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to post a little bit more now. As much as once or twice a year even! And if you&amp;rsquo;re interested, you&amp;rsquo;ll find that content here.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://carrano.org/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 22:50:50 -0400</pubDate><guid>https://carrano.org/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi! I’m Joe Carrano. This is my personal professional site. I&amp;rsquo;m a digital archivist at MIT Libraries where I work on saving both old and new bits for future generations. Previously, I was the &lt;a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/ndsr/documents/GUL_Proposal_Redacted.pdf">National Digital Stewardship Resident&lt;/a> at Georgetown University Library. I have a B.A. in history and political science from the University of Connecticut and dual master’s degrees from the University of Maryland, College Park, one in Library Science focusing on Archives and one U.S. History focusing on U.S. History. The site you&amp;rsquo;re on serves mainly as a place to put some (infrequent) blog posts on archives, history, and the digital world. If interested, stay and read more or contact me on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/joecar25">twitter&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://digipres.club">digipres.club&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>